Yuhao Zhang

CONTACT Information $\begin{tabular}{ll} E-mail: $yhzhang1994@gmail.com \\ $Website:$ $https://yhzhang.info/$ \end{tabular}$

Professional Experience Databricks, Mountain View, California USA

Software Engineer

December 2023 - present

R&D on applied AI/ML for systems, including automation and performance optimizations.

Microsoft Gray System Lab, California USA

Research Intern Summer 2021

Worked on machine learning systems research, focusing on factorized in-DBMS machine learning. Built a highly scalable system on top of Apache Spark that can outperform state-of-the-art by orders of magnitude.

VMware, Palo Alto, California USA

Software Engineer Intern

Summer 2019

Worked on the first in-DBMS deep learning system, allowing training and inference of deep learning models with TensorFlow on database-resident data. Integrated my research project, Cerebro, into the deep learning training infrastructure of Greenplum Database, boosting efficiency by over 10x. Contributed to the Apache MADlib project in Python and SQL. Lead the development of a major release. This project has been incorporated into Greenplum and production-ready for VMware's customers.

Opera Solutions, San Diego, California USA

Data Scientist Intern Summer 2018

Worked on a theatre scheduling & recommender system. Proposed new models and optimized the existing system.

EDUCATION

University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, California USA

Ph.D., Computer Science, November 2023

- Dissertation Topic: "High-throughput Data Systems for Deep Learning Workloads"
- Advisor: Prof. Arun Kumar

Nankai University, Tianjin, China

B.S., Theoretical Physics, June 2016

• Advisor: Prof. Xueqian Li and Prof. Yangang Miao

PAST RESEARCH INTERESTS AND IMPACT My past research is primarily on ML systems and large-scale data analytics systems, including systems powered by applied ML that enable novel applications and systems designed for ML to make data science easier and faster. Past and ongoing projects include systems for: large-scale distributed AutoML and training, distributed in-database deep learning, distributed large-scale GNN training, and video analytics and querying. All of my previous work has been released as open-source software. My past research on Cerebro and Cerebro-DS has been incorporated into the Apache MADlib open-source project and offered in Greenplum Database by VMware. The same projects have also been integrated with Spark, and Databricks is also reviewing the same project to offer to their customers. A prominent graph DBMS vendor is also interested in my work of Lotan.

PROJECTS Lotan: Bridging the Gap between GNNs and Scalable Graph Analytics Engines:

Recent advances in Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) have changed the landscape of modern graph analytics. The complexity of GNN training and the challenges of GNN scalability has also sparked interest from the systems community, with efforts to build systems that provide higher efficiency and schemes to reduce costs. However, we observe that many such systems basically "reinvent the wheel" of much work done in the database world on scalable graph analytics engines. Further, they often tightly couple the scalability treatments of graph data processing with that of GNN training, resulting in entangled complex problems and systems that often do not scale well on one of those axes.

This paper asks a fundamental question: How far can we push existing systems for scalable graph analytics and deep learning (DL) instead of building custom GNN systems? Are compromises inevitable on scalability and/or runtimes? We propose Lotan, the first scalable and optimized data system for full-batch GNN training with decoupled scaling that bridges the hitherto siloed worlds of graph analytics systems and DL systems. Lotan offers a series of technical innovations, including re-imagining GNN training as query plan-like dataflows, execution plan rewriting, optimized data movement between systems, a GNN-centric graph partitioning scheme, and the first known GNN model batching scheme. We prototyped Lotan on top of GraphX and PyTorch. An empirical evaluation using several real-world benchmark GNN workloads reveals a promising nuanced picture: Lotan significantly surpasses the scalability of state-of-the-art custom GNN systems, while often matching or being only slightly behind on time-to-accuracy metrics in some cases. We also show the impact of our system optimizations. Overall, our work shows that the GNN world can indeed benefit from building on top of scalable graph analytics engines. Lotan's new level of scalability can also empower new ML-oriented research on ever-larger graphs and GNNs.

Distributed Deep Learning on Data Systems (Cerebro-DS):

Deep learning (DL) is growing in popularity for many data analytics applications, including among enterprises. Large business-critical datasets in such settings typically reside in RDBMSs or other data systems. The DB community has long aimed to bring machine learning (ML) to DBMS-resident data. Given past lessons from in-DBMS ML and recent advances in scalable DL systems, DBMS and cloud vendors are increasingly interested in adding more DL support for DB-resident data. In this paper, we show that there is no single "best" approach to achieve that goal, and an interesting tradeoff space of approaches exists. We explain four canonical approaches, compare them analytically on multiple criteria (e.g., runtime efficiency and ease of governance) and compare them empirically with large-scale DL workloads. Our experiments and analyses show that it is non-trivial to meet all practical desiderata well and there is a Pareto frontier; for instance, some approaches are 3x-6x faster but fare worse on governance and portability. Our results and insights can help DBMS and cloud vendors design better DL support for DB users. The system is based on top of Postgres, Apache Spark, TensorFlow, and PyTorch.

Project homepage: https://adalabucsd.github.io/cerebro.html
Open-sourced release: https://github.com/makemebitter/cerebro-ds

Resource-efficient Distributed Deep Learning Model Selection and Training System (Cerebro):

Cerebro is a layered data platform for scalable deep learning. One of the biggest challenges for scalable deep learning is model selection, which is difficult and resource-heavy. This system provides high-level APIs for deep learning model selection and optimizes distributed deep learning training for model selection workloads. It adopts a new form of parallelism called Model Hopper Parallelism (MOP) and is the resource-optimal choice. It can expedite distributed deep learning training by 3x-10x compared to Horovod and TensorFlow Parameter Server. There are also subsequent works about bridging data systems (such as Apache Spark, Distributed databases, etc.) with distributed DL systems.

Project homepage: https://adalabucsd.github.io/cerebro.html
Open-sourced release: https://adalabucsd.github.io/cerebro-system

Video Querying System under Unbounded Vocabulary Setting (Panorama):

Panorama is a video querying system for object detection and classification. It is designed to tackle life-long learning or bounded vocabulary issues. Computer-vision-based video analytics systems often require *update* of the vocabulary as new classes/labels need to be added from time to time. Such updates involve re-training of the deep learning model, which requires expertise and is very time-consuming. Panorama is built to partially avoid and automate this process while expediting inference speed at the same time.

Project homepage: https://adalabucsd.github.io/panorama.html
Open-sourced release: https://github.com/makemebitter/Panorama-UCSD

ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, California USA

PhD Student 2017 - 2023

Includes current Ph.D. research, Ph.D. level coursework, and research/consulting projects. Courses taken: Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Data Mining & Analytics, Advanced Data Analytics, Computer Vision, Database Systems, Advanced Algorithms, Advanced Compilers, Principles of Programming Languages, Advanced Operating Systems, Computer Architecture, Introduction to Robotics

Collaborator for project DeepPostures: a deep learning library for identifying human postures from wearable devices data

2022 - 2023

Built and maintained project website (https://adalabucsd.github.io/DeepPostures/). Wrote documentation and made demos about the project. Provided software engineering support for other public health researchers. Conducted tests and data analysis for the project.

Teaching Assistant for CSE234: Data Systems for Machine Learning Winter 2021, Winter 2023 Helped to design and supervise a research-oriented course on machine learning systems. Mentored 12 master students with their course projects ranging from advanced implementation of cutting-edge research, to evaluation and surveying the state-of-art work, and to open-ended research. Did stand-in lectures.

Teaching Assistant for DSC102: Systems for Scalable Analytics

Winter 2020

Developed the first edition of course assignments and auto-grading programs with Python and Bash. The assignments involve Python Dask, Spark, AWS EC2/S3/EBS, and Kubernetes. These assignments have been adopted by the course ever since and used by 500+ students.

Texas A&M University, College Station, Texas USA

Research Intern Summer 2015

Worked on vision-based object tracking, modeling, and data analytics.

Institute of Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China

Research Intern Summer 2014

Theoretical physics research. Particle physics.

Nankai University, Tianjin, China

Research Assistant 2013 - 2016

Theoretical physics research. Black holes, gravity, and neutrinos. Resulted in two published papers.

PUBLICATIONS

Lotan: Bridging the Gap between GNNs and Scalable Graph Analytics Engines

Yuhao Zhang and Arun Kumar To appear at VLDB 2023

Some Damaging Delusions of Deep Learning Practice (and How to Avoid Them) Arun Kumar, Supun Nakandala, Yuhao Zhang KDD 2021 Deep Learning Day

Distributed Deep Learning on Data Systems: A Comparative Analysis of Approaches Yuhao Zhang, Arun Kumar, Frank McQuillan, Nandish Jayaram, Nikhil Kak, Ekta Khanna, Orhan Kislal, and Domino Valdano VLDB 2021

Cerebro: A Layered Data Platform for Scalable Deep Learning
Arun Kumar, Supun Nakandala, Yuhao Zhang, Side Li, Advitya Gemawat, and Kabir Nagrecha
CIDR 2021

Cerebro: A Data System for Optimized Deep Learning Model Selection Supun Nakandala, Yuhao Zhang, and Arun Kumar VLDB 2020

Panorama: A Data System for Unbounded Vocabulary Querying over Video Yuhao Zhang and Arun Kumar VLDB 2020

Cerebro: Efficient and Reproducible Model Selection on Deep Learning Systems Supun Nakandala, Yuhao Zhang, and Arun Kumar ACM SIGMOD 2019 DEEM Workshop

Physics Publications

Three-generation neutrino oscillations in curved spacetime Yuhao Zhang and Xueqian Li Nuclear Physics B, 2016

Self-regular black holes quantized by means of an analogue to hydrogen atoms Chang Liu, Yangang Miao, Yumei Wu, and Yuhao Zhang Advances in High Energy Physics, 2016

Presentations

Saturn: Efficient Multi-Model Deep Learning

Poster presentation, BayLearn 2023 October 2023

Lotan: Bridging the Gap between GNNs and Scalable Graph Analytics Engines
UCSD CNS Research Review
May 2023
UCSD HDSI Research Review
May 2023

High-throughput Data Systems for Deep Learning Workloads
UCSD Database Seminar April 2022

Distributed Deep Learning on Data Systems
VLDB 2021

August 2021

A Layered Data Platform for Scalable Deep Learning October 2020 UCSD Database Seminar UCSD CNS Research Review October 2020 Resource-Efficient Deep Learning Model Selection on Apache Spark Spark+AI Summit 2020 June 2020 UCSD Database Seminar May 2020 Cerebro: A Data System for Optimized Deep Learning Model Selection **VLDB 2020** September 2020 June 2020 UCSD Database Seminar Panorama: Unbounded Vocabulary Queries on Video **VLDB 2020** September 2020 UCSD Database Seminar June 2020 Poster presentation, UCSD CSE Research Open House January 2019 UCSD Database Seminar November 2019 Poster presentation, SoCal DB Day 2018 October 2018 Apache MADlib 1.17 Showcase VMware and online September 2019

SERVICE External reviewer: SIGMOD 2020, SIGMOD 2021, VLDB 2022

Reviewer: JMLR MLOSS 2022, SIGMOD 2024, VLDB 2024, VLDB Journal 2024, TKDE 2024,

ACM IKDD CODS-COMAD 2024

Misc SIGMOD 2021 Students and Postdocs in DB Panel Discussion June 2021

Honors and

Best Thesis Award, School of Physics, Nankai University, 2016 Awards Wang Kechang Scholarship for Academic Distinction, 2014

Gong-Neng Scholarship, 2013

Poling Academy Scholarship, 2012-2016

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming languages: Python, C/C++, Scala, Java, SQL, R
- Data platforms: Spark, Ray, Dask, PostgreSQL, Greenplum Database, Hadoop, Hive
- Machine learning frameworks: TensorFlow, PyTorch, Keras, xgBoost, LightGBM, Scikit-learn
- Other data analytics packages: Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, OpenCV, Scikit-image, Pillow/PIL
- Cloud/Cluster tools: AWS EC2/S3/EMR, Google Cloud, Azure, Kubernetes, Docker
- Miscs: MPI, MATLAB, Mathematica, CERN ROOT, CERN GEANT4